[SPEAKER_04]: So, I have a question.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what is the, so to say, value, or is there any value in dealing with, so to say, some theoretical aspects of dhamma?
[SPEAKER_04]: Not those that, so to say, directly interact with greed and aversion, so to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's, so to say, even
[SPEAKER_04]: Questions like if God exists or not, let's say, or any other, like materialism and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, eh... when it comes to those very kind of abstract theoretical things, especially when you cannot verify them for yourself, like it's going to be to some extent based on speculation, those are always the things that the... in the suttas, the Buddha would say that those are not... those are not the things that he declares, because they're not fundamental to the holy life.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually better to refrain from finding an answer to that type of question, rather than finding the answer that kind of corresponds to dhamma, because
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to, like you said, emphasize the freedom from greed, aversion and delusion aspect, eventually you would realize that the only reason that you sought an answer to the question, or that you thought that the question was important, is because somehow you thought that it was going to help you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when that goes away, it's like, you wouldn't have an answer to the question, but the question wouldn't appear to you as important.
[SPEAKER_02]: At least, this kind of question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Other ones, like, let's say, rebirth or, I don't know, other realms and things like that,
[SPEAKER_02]: You would then actually have a more practical basis to see what the Buddha meant when he referred to those things, whereas, initially, you would just kind of be taking it on faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you would, for example, be able to see how craving inevitably means that if you die... Like, it cannot be... it cannot have a beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not something that can sort of have popped up
[SPEAKER_02]: At some point, out of nowhere, and then kind of continued by its own momentum.
[SPEAKER_02]: But all of those things, initially, it's like, rather than trying to figure it out how it works or how it would be, it's if you discern your own mind and you see these things directly for yourself,
[SPEAKER_02]: By freeing yourself from the five hindrances and greed, aversion and delusion, then you would have the quote-unquote right answer, which, from the initial perspective, what you expected an answer to be probably would feel like inadequate, but now it doesn't, because you're not subject to all those doubts and pressures, which are really mostly emotional, rather than purely intellectual.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, what you mentioned about, like, craving and rebirth...
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, like, the fact that craving has no beginning, that does imply also that, kind of, there is no magic hand, so to say.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, there is no, like...
[SPEAKER_05]: Craving will not end by itself somehow in the future.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you would also come to realize that, because it's something that, when you discern it, through practice, through greater training, virtue, sense restraint, seclusion, it becomes apparent how every craving that you ever have
[SPEAKER_02]: It can only be there because previously... Like, when your mind is subject to craving, even though you don't want it to be subject to craving, it's always because in the past, you were acting out of some kind of pressure of that mind that made it worse.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like a fire that, without some fuel having been provided, at some point, that fire could not possibly be burning right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, having a fire that just started.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just come and there's a fire there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody lit it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody did anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a fire there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: It would actually be better to put the question aside, rather than just receive that as an answer, because then you would still be kind of intellectually believing in something that...
[SPEAKER_02]: It might actually stop you from really making the effort to see it for yourself, because you find safety in the intellectual answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's kind of like remaining in that
[SPEAKER_02]: Almost harder position of acknowledging like, okay, well, whichever answer I find...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to be... like I'm... it would only be adequate if I decide to settle for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I could always question it further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, instead of finding safety in those answers, you look for the real safety, which is freedom from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, like, the noble truths weren't, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Pronouncements about the nature of the universe, but rather about the thing that would want you to make to... that would make you want to know about the nature of the universe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those were the Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, entirely internal, quote-unquote, if you want to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, when the Buddha said that somebody who understands rightly would come to see that the arising of the world, the cessation of the world, is found within this very body.
[SPEAKER_02]: No larger than two meters.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, actually, you would come to see that all those notions that you might have, as kind of lofty and grandiose as it might be, if you investigate, even on a very kind of coarse level, you would realize, like, okay, there is a kind of bodily pressure
[SPEAKER_02]: That's making me want to think those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I wouldn't want...
[SPEAKER_02]: I wouldn't be able to think about those things if I was, let's say, very sleepy or very tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize, like, even on a very mundane level of reflection, all of these things don't, kind of, somehow... You cannot access something apart from your six sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you instead put that first and see everything else through that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if it's a sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, mental thought or image or phenomenon, you look at it through that lens.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of emphasizing the content of... and making it special, because it's a thought about God, or thought about the universe, thought about this, you see, okay, well, however special it is in its content, this has also arisen within this... six-sense body, within this... what was the word?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, but the word was like carcass, the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's within this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't have to deny any content of the ideas that you might have, because that's not where the solution lies.
[SPEAKER_02]: The solution lies in just becoming fully established in the knowledge that, oh, this dhamma has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you develop this passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Could you talk a little bit more about this passion?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it can easily be taken as something that I have to do, that I have to actively try to develop, but it's more like on the level of discerning the right kind of context, as you were talking about before.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, you can use that example as well, if you
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't see it on the right level, and you just take dispassion as another mental phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of take it to be right, because the content is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would overlook the fact that, well, I have passion towards this now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the dispassion has become the thing that I am obsessed with, almost.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you realize, well, that cannot possibly be... Like, it's going to be there to some extent initially, when you don't see your mind clearly, but
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole point is, you want to reach the point where that dispassion becomes, as you said, something you discern, something that's there in the things already, not something that you have to manufacture, because that's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were truly indifferent, if you were truly dispassionate, what need would there be to fabricate anything?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how do you practically discern that dispassion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well,
[SPEAKER_02]: You have multiple ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything that prevents you from fundamentally having that special privilege over the rest of your experience, reveals to you that instead of denying your sense of control and denying the input that you have over your experience, it becomes
[SPEAKER_02]: contained within something that's fundamentally not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you have developed passion towards dispassion, let's say, you ask yourself, okay, well, could I be contemplating and and doing all of this dispassion if I didn't have this body here right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: If I didn't have all these, even these ideas that I have about dispassion and so on, those ideas need to be arisen first in order for me to attend to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I were to forget it all about that, for some reason, I wouldn't be able to cultivate anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see, that dispassion now is not on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be now underlain by your desire, because it's now... kind of comes underneath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever standpoint you take, this is before that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the... that's when you develop, like... well, right view, because...
[SPEAKER_02]: The... basically, what...
[SPEAKER_02]: What you would have, when you just have a kind of self-made, quote-unquote, dispassion, is that view of annihilationism, or non-existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, even if you don't necessarily go to the point of, like, asserting that nothing exists, nothing is real, and everything will disintegrate when the body breaks apart, and the suttas would say, which is kind of the most extreme version of that view,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have that kind of attitude that takes denial of things as automatically more pure, you would fail to see that, well, that is now the thing that I am passionately established in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that wouldn't be the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the right view is when you undercut even that to the right discernment of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you could take whichever angle, but... Crailing, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, instead of... What would you... Why would you develop dispassion on the wrong level, practically?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would you develop dispassion on the wrong level?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, why would you be kind of passionately doing the dispassion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, because to some extent, I try to do it, and I don't see my doing in the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aha, but what do you not see, specifically?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I don't see my involvement in the things.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't see myself basically doing that.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't see...
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't... yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's one angle.
[SPEAKER_02]: But specifically, let's say, is there something that, let's say, in relation to craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: That you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, you can be thinking in terms of... That would be kind of the common thread of this passion.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, you want to abandon craving, you want to abandon lust, abandon greed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're trying to do that, like, genuinely.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that you're kind of being lazy or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you're making effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what is it that you're not seeing in regard to that specific craving that would be a problem?
[SPEAKER_05]: I try to get something from that conversation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, I try to trade, like, somehow.
[SPEAKER_05]: I try to... Like, yeah, I try to get something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but with the craving, is it like... where do you find craving, basically?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, you would be... when you're trying, quote-unquote, to do the dispassion, you have a notion of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, what would you be directing yourself towards?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I was going to say is, the craving that you are
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying to squish, you could say, is... well, it's not the craving that is actually kind of controlling you at that moment.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see something and you have some idea of what craving is, but that is within the actual craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's going to be
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's going to be rooted in you not seeing craving for what it actually is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to be focused in on something that fits your idea of what craving is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is going to be too narrow, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the... what is the problem there with that notion of craving that you have?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it just that it's too narrow?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is there something more direct that makes it an issue?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm trying to think of what I mean by too narrow... Because sometimes, let's say, let's give an example, like, I could, let's say, craving towards food, and I could develop a view that, like, well, as the Jains actually did, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody might have at some point realized, like, oh, yeah, I'm craving towards food.
[SPEAKER_02]: It induces sensuality in my mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they decide, okay, well, this is clearly a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I want to abandon craving, I need to abandon food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or anything else, like specific types of thoughts, when people would say, I shouldn't think about the future, because that's kind of... Craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: I shouldn't have memories about the past and remember things I did or... Is it what I didn't like?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would be like trying to
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it would be.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, specifically, there's like a kind of wrong notion there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That even if you, let's say, no matter what anybody tells you, unless you fix that wrong notion, you're still going to put the emphasis in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm kind of trying to think of a more original way of saying it, but, like, you are... You're focused on the content of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not seeing it on the level of your actual attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you recognize, like, factually, you have recognized your attitude in these things before, and, like, factually you've seen, okay, like, this is craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to be tying that actual recognition of what craving is to what you were doing at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the danger there is, when you then recollect that was craving before, that's now another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that doesn't necessarily mean that that's not a craving right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that thought isn't going to stand for craving in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, basically, the problem is that you would have developed a... you would have started to think about... it's almost... it's basically inevitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when you don't see the four no-truths, like, you will have...
[SPEAKER_02]: assumed or established an objective notion of what craving is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, that even if you are looking at your attitude
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within the context of you have put... You see, I'm sure when somebody has that view, they would be kind of feeling like they have the craving in their mind when they contemplate food or when they eat food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, why would they keep doing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It would become clear like, oh, well, I feel myself a craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It actually continues to feel like, yeah, that craving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: The the issue is like, by putting the emphasis on the blanket view that you developed beforehand, you don't realize that actually, yes, there might be some craving for food,
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing that's really supporting that whole setup of a mind that's passionate, in the most general sense, is that craving of you doing this whole thing to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you overlooking your attitude of... could be restlessness, could be doubt, could be any kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing that's controlling you from behind, supposedly making you do something good and wholesome, in other words, abandon craving for food, but actually, it is the more fundamental unwholesome thing that's kind of... how would you say that, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: The driving force?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's what's underneath.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you say it's like the theme of what you're doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like when the suttas would describe, you don't grasp a science and feature that will lead to the arising of longing and aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think often people would understand that as like, precisely in this context, like food.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I see a cake that has a nice shape or something, I shouldn't either...
[SPEAKER_02]: Ideally, I shouldn't look at the cake at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I look at it, I should somehow play with those perceptions, so that they don't...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't recognize, like, it's just a shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really... really a delicious cake.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a brown shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, actually, the sign and feature is that theme, that you would... the theme might not be there at that moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're suppressing it, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: The theme of this food is agreeable, is nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want more of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's delightful.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not a kind of thing that you're telling yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the implication of the thoughts that you will be having when you're actually acting out of craving for the cake.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those would be the kind of themes that are underlying your whole mental activity around this thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, in this context, let's say, if somebody who just developed that blanket view of rejecting food, because food is rooted in craving,
[SPEAKER_02]: The sign and feature there of the theme that they're developing, basically, or establishing themselves in, is a theme of aversion, theme of restlessness, theme of denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they don't see that as a sign or feature that leads to the arising of states of distress, of agitation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that's what it means to... because, see, the sutta doesn't say... it doesn't look at sights on account of which lust and aversion would arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's almost presupposed, if you're keeping virtue and have some common sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's even much more subtle than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's having seen a sight
[SPEAKER_02]: Having heard a sound, having smelled a smell, he doesn't grasp at signs and features on account of which unwholesome states will arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... that's already at a level where you wouldn't be attending to those things, like, full-on, carelessly, because that already comes within the virtue, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's just obvious.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is taking you towards breaking the precept.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now, within that, when there are things that are, let's say, not unwholesome to look at, not unwholesome to smell, not unwholesome to taste, now you have to look at what are the themes, the background themes that I am maintaining in regard to this whatever object I'm engaging with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, it's important to emphasize that it's something that becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's pre-verbal, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like a thing that you are saying to yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the most kind of acute, subtle context behind this whole situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could almost look at it as like... a very coarse example of it would be like the motivation when you're doing something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like if you're talking to someone and you're, let's say, using very polite language on the outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, your ulterior motive there, you're not necessarily thinking that in your mind, like, that, let's say, I'm angry towards this person, and I really despise what they did, but I'm trying to...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm acting out of that anger, but I'm talking to them in a very polite way, because I hope that through that, they will not do that thing that I don't want them to do again.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that whole sign and feature, that whole theme, that you're not necessarily aware of, is a theme of aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even though, on that external level, you might not even be clear to yourself about the fact that that's the theme.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, those are... that's what the Buddha meant with grasping signs and features, and in this context, going back to what we were describing, you would have to extend this principle to anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you would start to abandon these views, because you would realize, like, well, there's no value in this.
[SPEAKER_02]: If, even if it's the right thing that I thought I got from the Buddha, there's no value in cultivating something that leads to the increase of lust or leads to the increase of aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it does, that means that's not what the Buddha was actually meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you would start to see that
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the actual dispassion is a theme that's at that background level, on the level of mind, of the level of citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: You start to realize, like, okay, there's absolutely no benefit if I am thinking thoughts about death, and thoughts about sickness, and thoughts about losing everything, if the mind, if that animal that's kind of indirectly
[SPEAKER_02]: There at the same time, but but it's not the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that animal is getting actually agitated and less pliable on account of you thinking those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, it might be steadily kind of, um...
[SPEAKER_02]: Off-putting to reflect on those things, but then that's something that you would begin to be able to distinguish for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, what's the right type of saṃvegā?
[SPEAKER_02]: Of being moved by something, as the Buddha said, things that are worth being moved by.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the difference between that and just winding myself up for no for no purpose?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you see, the wrong type of winding yourself up, let's say, would be more restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, but actually, you would realize, like, if I stop doing this, I'm actually more inclined towards an wholesome stance than the opposite.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you say that again?
[SPEAKER_02]: The wrong kind of working yourself... Like, if you're just thinking about death, thinking about sickness, thinking about aging... Like, the whole time, kind of... Yeah, but not paying any attention at all to, like, what is the attitude behind this.
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of just assume that that contemplation in itself is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mechanically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a mantra, almost.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just... By doing that, you would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: You would be putting yourself in a position... you're acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, actually, your mind would be... like, right now, it's focused on this, because you're forcefully keeping it there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you were to bring, let's say, let it loose and go wherever it wants, you would find that the unwholesome directions have been either maintained or maybe even increased, because you were acting out of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, if you were doing it with some recognition of like, okay, no, my mind was actually obsessed with life and intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intoxicated with life, intoxicated with youth, intoxicated with health, as a citizen would say.
[SPEAKER_02]: And based on having recognized that theme, you cultivate this opposite theme.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it's like, yeah, you might factually feel a sense of, like, urgency, a sense of disenchantment, even, like, almost, like, to the point of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Of being moved by it, like, oh, I should be more heedful, I should be more careful with my actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, that is now actually taking you away from the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's leading you in the direction of... in the right direction, and it's... even if it's not, let's say, perfectly peaceful, as it would be to just ignore that you would... that you are subject to these things,
[SPEAKER_02]: It is leading to a decrease of unwholesome states overall.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why... it's like... that simile of the cook, actually, the Chinese version, has a very nice passage that doesn't occur in the Pali one.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, it was the very thing that we were discussing in that sign of the mind talk.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, if the cook
[SPEAKER_02]: presents a dish to the king based on his own ideas, his preconceived notions of what the king should be eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rather than actually paying attention to the preferences of the king and where he inclines, then that's why he will never be able to basically be a good cook and get promoted and rewarded by the king.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's that same thing like you have, on account of reading, on account of contemplating, you have developed a blanket view that this food, that this type of contemplation is good because, you know, it's about death, it's about
[SPEAKER_02]: Sickness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, sure, there are probably worse things to think about, but if you do it without paying any attention to where you're at, your whole attitude behind it, and you're not even aware, like I said,
[SPEAKER_02]: That there was some intoxication, that there was some wrong attitude there, and you're just doing it because the Buddha said I should do this.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are cooking for yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why you want to...
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter what the contemplation is, especially when you're not sufficiently familiar with the science of your mind and you haven't got the right view yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: You should
[SPEAKER_02]: Your main contemplation should be like, what's my attitude behind this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what will keep you in check and see if you are doubtful, like, well, I'm not sure what my attitude behind this is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you should actually redirect your effort to clarifying that most of the time, rather than just continuing to... because what are you going to be making foods, like, cooking dishes with... based on probability?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, I think this one is more likely to
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, it's better to actually... okay, well, instead of doing this, let me look at the king and see what's actually going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: What the mind really needs?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, like, what the mind needs in terms of... if it has been inclining in... you actually see it inclining in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize, okay, now contemplating death will take it away from that wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just don't know, and you just keep doing it, you will be... inevitably, you will be winding yourself up unnecessarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no need to make effort, unless there are unwholesome states present.
[SPEAKER_02]: That becomes your unwholesome state, your restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's exactly what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have four right strivings.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have abandoning arisen unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have making sure that unwholesome states don't arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have making sure that wholesome states arise and making sure that wholesome states are maintained.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's an effort in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you only do the other three,
[SPEAKER_02]: Something's going to be wrong, because sometimes you have a, at least, more wholesome state of mind, where there isn't anything harmful at the time, and you need to be able to recognize that, and learn how to protect it, rather than constantly assuming, like, no, no, no, there must be something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, the king needs more food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just by default, he needs.
[SPEAKER_02]: He needs more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, he just had enough and that's good for now.